<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A supplicacyon for the beggers</title>
            <author>Fish, Simon, d. 1531.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00757</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845344</idno>
  <idno type="VID">10237</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240873792</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 10883</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S109699</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99845344e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00757)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 40:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A supplicacyon for the beggers</title>
                  <author>Fish, Simon, d. 1531.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Grapheus?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Antwerp? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1529?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Simon Fish.</note>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Answered by STC 18092: Fisher, John.  A sermon had at Paules .. upon quinquagesim Sonday.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">England --  Economic conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>pfs </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front xml:lang="eng">
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:10237:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10237:1"/>
            <p>¶ A Supplicacyon for the Beggers.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb facs="tcp:10237:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KING OVRE souereygne lorde.</head>
            <p>MOst lamentably compleyneth theyre wofull mysery vnto youre highnes youre poore daily bedemē the wret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched hidous monstres (on whome scarcely for horror any yie dare lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke) the foule vnhappy sorte of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres, and other sore people, nedy, impotent, blinde, lame, and sike, that live onely by almesse, howe that theyre nombre is daily so sore encreased that all the almesse of all the weldis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed people of this youre realme is not halfe ynough for to susteine theim, but that for verey constreint they die for hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And this most pestilent mischief is comen vppon you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re saide poore beedmē by the reason that there is yn the tymes of youre noble predecessours passed craftily crept ynto this your realme an other sort (not of impotent but) of strong puis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>saunt and counterfeit holy, and ydell beggers and vacabundes whiche syns the tyme of theyre first entre by all the craft and wilinesse of Satan are nowe encreased vnder your sight not onely into a great nōbre, but also ynto a kingdome. These are (not the herdes, but the rauinous wolues going in herdes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing deuouring the flocke) the Bisshoppes, Abbottes, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, Deacons, Archedeacons, Suffraganes, Prestes, Monkes Chanons, Freres, Pardoners and Somners. And who is abill to nōbre this idell rauinous sort whiche (setting all laboure a side) haue begged so importunatly that they haue gotten ynto theyre hondes more then the therd part of all youre Realme. The goodliest lordshippes, maners, londes, and territories, are
<pb facs="tcp:10237:2"/> theyrs. Besides this they haue the tenth part af all the corne, medowe, pasture, grasse, wolle, coltes, calues, lambes, pigges, gese, and chikens. Ouer and bisides the tenth part of euery ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes wages the tenth part of the wolle, milke, hony, waxe chese, and butter. Ye and they loke so narowly vppon theyre proufittes that the poore wyues must be countable to theym of euery tenth eg or elles she gettith not her ryghtes at ester shalbe taken as an heretike, hereto haue they theire foure of fering daies. whate money pull they yn by probates of testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, priuy tithes, and by mennes offeringes to theyre pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gremages, and at theyre first masses? Euery man and childe that is buried must pay sumwhat for masses and diriges to be song for him or elles they will accuse the dedes frendes and executours of heresie. whate money get they by mortuaries, by hearing of confessions (and yet they wil kepe therof no counceyle) by halowing of churches altares super altares cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelles and belles, by cursing of men and absoluing theim agein for money? what a multitude of money gather the pardoners in a yere? Howe moche money get the Somners by extorcion yn a yere, by assityng the people to the commissaries court and afterward releasing thapparaūce for money? Finally, the infi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite nombre of begging freres whate get they yn a yere? He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re if it please your grace to marke ye shall se a thing farre out of ioynt. There are withyn youre realme of Englond .lij. thousand parisshe churches. And this stonding that there be but tenne houshouldes yn euery parisshe yet are there fiue hundreth thousand and twenty thousand houshouldes. And of euery of these houshouldes hath euery of the fiue ordres of freres a peny a quarter for euery ordre, that is for all the fiue ordres fiue pens a quarter for every house. That is for all
<pb facs="tcp:10237:3"/> the fiue ordres .xx. d, a yere of euery house. Summa fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thousand and twenty thousand quarters of angels. That is .cclx. thousand half angels. Summa .cxxx. thousand an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gels. Summa totalis .xliij. thousand poundes and .cccxxxiij. li. vi. s. viij. d. sterling. wherof not foure hundreth yeres passed they had not one peny. Oh greuous and peynfull exactiōs thus yerely to be paied. from the whiche the people of your nobill predecessours the kinges of the aunciēt Britōs euer stode fre And this wil they haue or els they wil {pro}cure him that will not giue it theim to be takē as an heretike. whate tiraunt euer oppressed the people like this cruell and vengeable genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion? whate subiectes shall be abill to helpe theire prince that be after this facion yerely polled? whate good christen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can be abill to socoure vs pore lepres blinde sore, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that be thus yerely oppressed? Is it any merueille that you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re people so compleine of pouertie? Is it any merueile that the taxes fiftenes and subsidies that your grace most tenderly of great cōpassion hath taken emong your people to defend the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>im from the thretened ruine of theire comon welth haue bin so sloughtfully, ye painfully leuied? Seing that almost the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most peny that mought haue bin leuied hath ben gathered bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yerely by this rauinous cruell and insatiabill generacion The danes nether the saxons yn the time of the auncient Bri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tons shulde neuer haue ben abill to haue brought theire armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es from so farre hither ynto your lond to haue conquered it if they had had at that time suche a sort of idell glotons to fin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de at home. The nobill king Arthur had neuer ben abill to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue caried his armie to the fote of the mountaines to resist the coming downe of lucius the Emperoure if suche yerely exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions had ben taken of his people. The grekes had neuer ben
<pb facs="tcp:10237:3"/> abill to haue so long cōtinued at the siege of Troie if they had had at home suche an idell sort of cormorauntes to finde. The auncient Romains had neuer ben abil to haue put all the hole worlde vnder theyre obeisaunce if theyre people had byn thus yerely oppressed. The Turke nowe yn youre tyme shulde neuer be abill to get so moche grounde of cristendome if he had yn his empire suche a sort of locustes to deuoure his substaunce. Ley then these sommes to the forseid therd part of the possessions of the realme that ye may se whether it drawe nighe vnto the half of the hole substaunce of the real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me or not, So shall ye finde that it draweth ferre aboue. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we let vs then compare the nombre of this vnkind idell sort vnto the nombre of the laye people and we shall se whether it be indifferently shifted or not that they shuld haue half. Compare theim to the nombre of men, so are they not the .C. person. Compare theim to men wimen and children, then are they not the .CCCC. parson yn nombre. One part therfore yn foure hundreth partes deuided were to moche for theim except they did laboure. whate an vnequal burthen is it that they haue half with the multitude and are not the .CCCC. parson of theire nombre? whate tongue is abill to tell that euer there was eny comon welth so sore oppressed sins the worlde first began?</p>
            <p>¶And whate do al these gredy sort of sturdy idell holy the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with these yerely exactions that they take of the people? Truely nothing but exempt theim silues from thobedience of your grace. Nothing but translate all rule power lordis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hippe auctorite obedience and dignite from your grace vnto theim. Nothing but that all your subiectes shulde fall vnto disobedience and rebellion ageinst your grace and be vnder
<pb facs="tcp:10237:4"/> theym. As they did vnto your nobill predecessour king Iohn: whiche forbicause that he wolde haue punisshed certeyn tray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours that had conspired with the frenche king to haue depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him frō his crowne and dignite (emong the whiche a cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke called Stephen whome afterward ageinst the kinges will the Pope made Bisshoppe of Caunterbury was one) enterdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Lond. For the whiche mater your most nobill realme wrongfully (alas for shame) hath stōd tributary (not vnto any kind temporall prince, but vnto a cruell deuelisshe bloudsup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per dronkē in the bloude of the sayntes and marters of christ) euer sins. Here were an holy sort of prelates that thus cruelly coude punisshe suche a rightuous kinge, all his realme, ād suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession for doing right.</p>
            <p>¶ Here were a charitable sort of holy men that coude thus enterdite an hole realme, and plucke awey thobediēce of the people from theyre naturall liege lorde and kinge, for none other cause but for his rightuousnesse. Here were a blissed sort not of meke herdes but of bloudsuppers that coude set the frenche king vppon suche a rightuous prince to cause hym to lose his crowne and dignite to make effusion of the bloude of his people, oneles this good and blissed king of grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te compassion, more fearing and lamenting the sheding of the bloude of his people then the losse of his crowne and dignite agaynst all right and conscience had submitted him silf vnto theym. O case most horrible that euer so nobill a king Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and succession shulde thus be made to stoupe to suche a sort of bloudsuppers. where was his swerde, power, crowne, and dignite become wherby he mought haue done iustice yn this maner? where was their obediēce become that shuld haue byn subiect vnder his highe power yn this mater? Ye where
<pb facs="tcp:10237:4"/> was the obedience of all his subiectes become that for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the comon welth shulde haue holpen him manfully to haue resisted these bloudsuppers to the shedinge of theyre bloude? was not all to gither by theyre polycy translated frō this good king vnto theim. Ye and what do they more? Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ely nothing but applie theym silues by all the sleyghtes they may to haue to do with euery mannes wife, euery mānes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughter and euery mannes mayde that cukkoldrie and baudr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ie shulde reigne ouer all emong your subiectes, that no mā sh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ulde knowe his owne childe that theyre bastardes might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the possessions of euery man to put the right begotten children clere beside theire inheritaunce yn subuersion of all estates and godly ordre. These be they that by theire abstey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from mariage do let the generation of the people wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by all the realme at length if it shulde be continued shall be made desert and inhabitable.</p>
            <p>¶ These be they that haue made an hundreth thousand y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell hores yn your realme whiche wolde haue gotten theyre lyuing honestly, yn the swete of theyre faces had not theyre superfluous rychesse illected theym to vnclene lust and ydel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. These be they that corrupt the hole generation of mā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kind yn your realme, that catche the pokkes of one woman. and bere theym to an other, that be brent wyth one woman, and bere it to an other, that catche the lepry of one woman, and bere it to an other, ye some one of theym shall bost emong his felawes that he hath medled with an hundreth wymen. These be they that when they haue ones drawē mennes wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to suche incontinēcy spende awey theire husbondes goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des make the wimen to runne awey from theire husbondes, ye, rynne awey them silues both with wif ād goodes, bring
<pb facs="tcp:10237:5"/> both man wife and children to ydelnesse theft and beggeri. Ye who is abill to nombre the greate and brode botomles oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean see full of euilles that this mischeuous and sinful genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion may laufully bring vppon vs vnponisshed. where is you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re swerde, power, crowne, and dignite, become that shuld pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nisshe (by punisshement of deth euen as other men are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisshed) the felonies, rapes, murdres, and treasons cōmitted by this sinfull generaciō? where is theire obedience become that shulde be vnder your hyghe power yn this mater? ys not all to gither translated and exempt frō your grace vnto theim? yes truely. whate an infinite nombre of people might haue bē encreased to haue peopled the realme if these sort of folke had bē maried like other men. whate breche of matrimonie is there brought yn by theim? suche truely as was neuer sins the worlde began emong the hole multitude of the hethen.</p>
            <p>¶ who is she that wil set her hondes to worke to get .iij.d. a day and may haue at lest .xx.d. a day to slepe an houre with a frere, a monke, or a prest? what is he that wolde laboure for a grote a day and may haue at lest .xij.d. a day to be baude to a prest, a monke, or a frere? whate a sort are there of thei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me that mari prestes souereigne ladies but to cloke the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes yncontinency and that they may haue a liuing of the prest theime silues for theire laboure? Howe many thousandes doth suche lubricite bring to beggery theft and idelnesse whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che shuld haue kept theire good name and haue set theim sil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues to worke had not ben this excesse treasure of the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtie?? whate honest man dare take any man or woman yn his seruice that hath bē at suche a scole with a spiritual mā? Oh the greuous shipwrak of the comon welth, whiche yn aunciēt time bifore the coming yn of these rauinous wolues
<pb facs="tcp:10237:5"/> was so prosperous: that then there were but fewe theues: ye theft was at that tyme so rare that Cesar was not cōpellid to make penalite of deth vppon felony as your grace may well perceyue yn his institutes. There was also at that tyme but fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we pore people and yet they did not begge but there was giuē theim ynough vnaxed, for there was at that time none of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se rauinous wolues to axe it from theim as it apperith yn the actes of thappostles. Is it any merueill though there be nowe so many beggers, theues, and ydell people? Nay truely.</p>
            <p>¶ whate remedy: make lawes ageynst theim. I am yn doubt whether ye be able: Are they not stronger in your owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament house then your silfe? whate a nombre of Bisshopes' abbotes' and priours are lordes of your parliament? are not all the lerned men in your realme in fee with theim to speake yn your parliament house for theim ageinst your crowne’ digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te’ and comon welth of your realme a fewe of youre owne lerned counsell onely excepted? whate lawe can he made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geinst theim that may be aduaylable? who is he (though he be greued never so sore) for the murdre of his anucestre rauisshe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of his wyfe, of his doughter, robbery, trespas, maiheme, dette, or eny other offence dare ley it to theyre charge by any wey of accion, and if he do then is he by and by by theyre wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynesse accused of heresie. ye they will so handle him or he pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sse that except he will bere a fagot for theyre pleasure he shal be excommunicate and then be all his accions dasshed. So cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue are your lawes vnto theym that no man that they lyst to excōmunicat may be admitted to sue any accion in any of your courtes. If eny mā yn your sessions dare be so hardy to endyte a prest of eny suche cryme he hath or the yere go out suche a yoke of heresye leyd in his necke that it maketh him wisshe
<pb facs="tcp:10237:6"/> that he had not done it. Your grace may se whate a worke there is in London, howe the bisshoppe rageth for endyting of certayn curates of extorcion and incontinency the last ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in the warmoll quest. Had not Richard hunne commenced accyon of premunire ageinst a prest he had bin yet a lyue and none eretik at all but an honest man.</p>
            <p>¶Dyd not dyuers of your noble progenitours seynge theyre crowne and dignite runne ynto ruyne and to be thus craftely translated ynto the hondes of this myscheuous generacyon make dyuers statutes for the reformacyon therof, emong whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the statute of mortmayne was one? to the intent that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that tyme they shulde haue no more gyuen vnto theim. But whate avayled it? haue they not gotten ynto theyre hon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des more londes sins then eny duke yn ynglond hath, the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute notwithstonding? Ye haue they not for all that transla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted ynto theyre hondes from your grace half your kyngdome thoroughly? The hole name as reason is for the auncientie of your kyngdome whiche was bifore theyrs and out of the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che theyrs is growen onely abiding with your grace? and of one kyngdome made tweyne: the spirituall kyngdome (as they call it) for they wyll be named first, And your temporall kingdome, And whiche of these .ij. kingdomes suppose ye is li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to ouergrowe the other? ye to put the other clere out of me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mory? Truely the kingdome of the bloudsuppers for to theym is giuen daily out of your kingdome. And that that is ones gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen theim comith neuer from theim agein. Suche lawes haue they that none of theim may nether gyue nor sell nothing. whate lawe can be made so stronge ageinst theim that they other with money or elles with other policy will not breake and set at nought? whate kingdome can endure that euer gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uith
<pb facs="tcp:10237:6"/> thus from him and receyueth nothing agein? O howe all the substaūce of your Realme forthwith your swerde, power, crowne, dignite, and obedience of your people, rynneth hed-long ynto the insaciabill whyrlepole of these gredi goulafres to be swalowed and devoured.</p>
            <p>¶Nether haue they eny other coloure to gather these yerely exaccions ynto theyre hondes but that they sey they pray for vs to God to delyuer our soules out of the paynes of purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri without whose prayer they sey or at lest without the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes pardon we coude neuer be deliuered thens whiche if it be true then is it good reason that we gyue theim all these thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges all were it C times as moche, But there be many men of greate litterature and iudgement that for the love they haue vnto the trouth and vnto the comen welth haue not feared to put theim silf ynto the greatest infamie that may be, in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of all the world, ye yn perill of deth to declare theyre oppinion in this mather whiche is that there is no purgatory but that it is a thing inuented by the couitousnesse of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualtie onely to translate all kingdomes from other princes vnto theim and that there is not one word spoken of hit in al holy scripture. They sey also that if there were a purgatory And also if that the pope with his pardons for money may de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuer one soule thēs: he may deliuer him aswel without money if he may deliuer one, he may deliuer a thousand: yf he may deliuer a thousand he may deliuer theim all, ād so destroy pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatory. And then is he a cruell tyraunt without all charite if he kepe theim there in pryson and in paine till men will giue him money.</p>
            
            <p>¶Lyke wyse saie they of all the hole sort of the spiritueltie that if they will not pray for no mā but for theim that gyue theim money they are tyrauntes ād lakke charite,
<pb facs="tcp:10237:7"/> and suffer those soules to be punisshed ād payned vncherita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly for lacke of theyre prayers. These sort of folkes they call heretikes, these they burne, these they rage ageinst, put to opē shame and make theim bere fagottes. But whether they be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes or no, well I wote that this purgatory and the Popes pardons is all the cause of translaciō of your kingdome so fast into their hondes wherfore it is manifest it can not be of ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist, for he gaue more to the temporall kingdome, he hym silfe paid tribute to Cesar he toke nothing frō hym but taught that the highe powers shuld be alweys obeid ye he him silf (althou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh he were most fre lorde of all and innocent) was obedient vnto the highe powers vnto deth. This is the great scabbe why they will not let the newe testament go a brode yn your moder tong lest men shulde espie that they by theyre cloked ypochrisi do translate thus fast your kingdome into theyre hō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, that they are not obedient vnto your highe power, that they are cruell, vnclene, vnmerciful, and ypochrites, that thei seke not the honour of Christ but their owne, that remission of sinnes are not giuen by the popes pardon, but by Christ, for the sure feith and trust that we haue in him. Here may your grace well perceyue that except ye suffer theyre ypocrisie to be disclosed all is like to runne ynto theire hondes and as long as it is couered so long shall it seme to euery mā to be a greate ympiete not to gyue theim. For this I am sure your grace thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth (as the truth is) I am as good a man as my father, whye may I not aswell gyue theim as moche as my father did. And of this mynd I am sure are all the loordes knightes squire gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tilmen and yemen in englond, ye and vntill it be disclosed all your peoole will thinke that your statute of mortmayne was never made with no good conscience seing that it taketh a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wey
<pb facs="tcp:10237:7"/> the liberte of your people in that they may not as laufully by theire soules out of purgatory by gyuing to the spiritualte as their predecessours did in tymes passed.</p>
            <p>¶wherfore if ye will eschewe the ruyne of your crowne and dignite let theire ypocrisye be vttered and that shalbe more spedfull in this mater then all the lawes that may be made be they never so stronge. For to make a lawe for to punisshe eny offender except it were more for to giue other men an ensam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to beware to committe suche like offence, whate shuld yt avayle. Did not doctour Alyn most presumptuously nowe yn your tyme ageynst all his allegiaunce all that ever he coude to pull from you the knowlege of suche plees as long vnto your hyghe courtes vnto an other court in derogacion of your cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne and dignite? Did not also doctor Horsey and his compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces most heynously as all the world knoweth murdre in pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that honest marchaunt Richard hunne? For that he sued your writ of premunire against a prest that wrongfully held him in ple in a spirituall court for a mater wherof the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege belonged vnto your hyghe courtes. And whate punisshe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was there done that eny man may take example of to be ware of lyke offence? truely none but that the one payd fiue hundreth poundes (as it is said to the bildinge of your sterre chamber) and when that payment was ones passed the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyns of his kingdome (bicause he faught so manfully ageynst your crowne and dignite) haue heped to him benefice vpon be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefice so that he is rewarded tenne tymes as moche. The other as it is seid payde sixe hundreth poundes for him and his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plices whiche for bicause that he had lyke wise faught so man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ageynst your crowne and dignite was ymmediatly (as he had opteyned your most gracyous pardon) promoted by the
<pb facs="tcp:10237:8"/> capiteynes of his kingdome with benefice vpon benefice to the value of .iiij. tymes as moche. who can take example of this punisshement to be ware of suche like offence? who is he of theyre kingdome that will not rather take courage to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte lyke offence seyng the promocions that fill to this men for theyre so offending. So weke and blunt is your swerde to strike at one of the offenders of this croked and peruers generacyon.</p>
            <p>¶And this is by the reason that the chief instrument of your lawe ye the chief of your counsell and he whiche hath youre swerde in his hond to whome also all the other instrumentes are obedient is alweys a spirituell man whiche hath euer su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che an inordinate loue vnto his owne kingdome that he will mainteyn that, though all the temporall kingdoms and comō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>welth of the worlde shulde therfore vtterly be vndone, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re leue we out the gretest mater of all lest that we declaring suche an horrible carayn of euyll ageinst the ministres of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite shulde seme to declare the one onely faute or rather the ignoraunce of oure best beloued ministre of rightousnesse whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is to be hid till he may be lerned by these small enormitees that we haue spoken of to knowe it pleynly him silf. But whate remedy to releue vs your poore sike lame and sore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demen? To make many hospitals for the relief of the poore people? Nay truely. The moo the worse, for euer the fatte of the hole foundacion hangeth on the prestes berdes. Dyuers of your noble predecessours kinges of this realme haue gyuen londes to monasteries to giue a certein somme of money yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the poore people wherof for the aunciente of the tyme they giue neuer one peny, They haue lyke wise giuen to thē to haue a certeyn masses said daily for theim wherof they
<pb facs="tcp:10237:8"/> sey neuer one. If the Abbot of westminster shulde sing euery day as many masses for his founders as he is bounde to do by his foundacion .M, monkes were to fewe. wherfore if your grace will bilde a sure hospitall that neuer shall faile to rele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vs all your poore bedemē, so take from them all these thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Set these sturdy lobies a brode in the world to get theim wiues of theire owne, to get theire liuing with their labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in the swete of theire faces according to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god. Gene .iij. to gyue other idell people by theire ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample occasion to go to laboure. Tye these holy idell theues to the cartes to be whipped naked about euery market towne til they will fall to laboure that they by theyre īportunate beg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging take not awey the almesse that the good christen people wolde giue vnto vs sore impotent miserable people your bede men. Then shall aswell the nombre of oure forsaid monstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous sort as of the baudes, hores theues, and idell people decre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ace. Then shall these great yerely exaccions cease. Then shall not youre swerde, power, crowne, dignite, and obedience of your people, be translated from you. Then shall you haue full obedience of your people. Then shall the idell people be set to worke. Then shall matrimony be moche better kept. Then shal the generation of your people be encreased, Then shall your comons encrease in richesse. Then shall the gospell be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. Then shall none begge oure almesse from vs. Then shal we haue ynough and more then shall fuffice vs, whiche shall be the best hospitall that euer was founded for vs, Then shall we daily pray to god for your most noble estate lōg to endure.</p>
            <closer>Domine saluum fac regem.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>